目覚めては繰り返す
Day after day, I awake in a daze,
mezamete ha kurikaesu nemui asa ha
目覚めては繰り返す　眠い朝は
眠い朝は
襟のタイをきつく締め
And fasten my collar tightly.
eri no tai wo kitsuku shime
襟のタイをきつく締め
教室のドアくぐると
As I walk through the door to my classroom,
kyoushitsu no doa kuguru to hon no sukoshi
教室のドアくぐるとほんの少し
ほんの少し胸を張って歩き出せる
I have the slightest bit of pride.
mune wo hatte arukidaseru
胸を張って歩き出せる
Then a wind rushed through that normal, everyday life.
sonna nichijou ni fukinukeru kaze
そんな日常に吹き抜ける風
そんな日常に
吹き抜ける風
聞こえた気がした　感じた気がしたんだ
I have a feeling I can hear it,
kikoeta ki ga shita
聞こえた気がした
I have a feeling I can sense it,
kanjita ki ga shitanda
感じた気がしたんだ
震えだす 今この胸で
Beginning to tremble within my chest.
furuedasu ima kono mune de
震え出す今この胸で
I have a feeling it's on its way,
mou kuru ki ga shita
もう来る気がした
As the millions of stars began to disappear,
ikuoku no hoshi ga kiesatteku no wo
幾億の星が消え去ってくのを
I sent them on their way,
miokutta
見送った
見送った 手を振った
Waving my hand,
te wo futta
手を振った
良かったねと
Whispering, "Congratulations".
yokatta ne, to
よかったね、と
I understand several consciousnesses were fused into her.
この子　一度にたくさんの意識と同化しちゃったんだってねぇ
Infirmary (Closed Off)
Yeah.
ああ
It's my fault.
アタシのせいねぇ
いや　ゆりはリーダーとして最高の仕事をしたよ
No, you did a great job as leader.
戦線の最大の危機を回避した
You kept the Battlefront afloat during its greatest crisis.
Besides, no one could have known there would be so many of her waiting for us.
それに　誰も想像できなかったさ
ギルドに大量の分身を配置して　待ち構えているなんてさ
それに　あれは奏のッ
And that was all Kanade's-
...the other Kanade's plot.
冷酷な奏の考えた作戦で
Even then, they were still so like Kanade, so I doubt I could have done anything better myself.
それはやっぱり奏だから
仕方がなかったことだと思う
I guess so.
そう
I feel better hearing you say that.
そう言ってくれると助かるけど
なぁ　病院なんてない
Hey... You told me there aren't any hospitals because no one gets sick, right?
誰も病まないからって言ってたじゃないか
Then why won't you wake up?
じゃ何で　起きてくれないんだ　畜生
God damn it.
Headmaster's Room
There's no such precedence.
これまでにないことです
Anti-Tenshi Operation HQ
We've never seen Tenshi like that before.
天使のあんな状態は初めてです
このまま二度と目覚めないと言うことも
There's a possibility she might never wake up.
場合によってはあり得るかもしれません
That would be the greatest irregularity so far, if so. I'm sure she'll wake up.
それこそイレギュラーな事態よ　目覚めるわ
She'll open her eyes and just say she overslept.
いつか目覚めて
ただ寝過ぎただけという結果に変わる
その時の彼女はどの彼女なんだ
When she does wake up, which "her" will she be?
おーーッ　椎名が喋った
Holy crap! Shiina spoke!
That only proves this really is a critical issue!
これは相当重要な問題だってことだよ
And she's right.
まさにそう
それが問題よ
That's the real question.
で　どっちの天使なんだ
So, which Tenshi is it gonna be?
It has to be the original Tenshi.
それは最初の天使だよ　一緒に釣りをした
The one we went fishing with.
だが俺たちを襲った意識はすべて好戦的で　冷酷だった
But all the Tenshi that attacked us were aggressive and cruel.
Just talking numbers, there were like 100 evil ones to the single original.
数で行けば　百対一ぐらいだぜ
今なぜ意識を失っているのか
Why doesn't she just wake up already?
Don't you think it's because of all those evil minds crowding in her head, messing stuff up and pushing things around?
たぶん　そのたくさんの意識があいつの小さな頭の中で
こう　ぐちゃぐちゃになって
ひどいことになってるからじゃねぇのか
じゃあ　目覚めるとしたら
So you're saying when she wakes up, the 100 minds could possibly overtake her?
百の意識で目覚めることもあるの
So mathematically speaking, I'd say we only have about a 1% chance of seeing the original Tenshi.
割合で言えば
元のままで目覚める可能性は約１パーセントってことねぇ
どうする
So now what?
I already have a countermeasure planned out.
手は打ってあるわ
竹山君を天使エリアに送り込んだ
I've sent Takeyama-kun, along with some people who can translate the software manual, to Tenshi's Domain.
マニュアル翻訳ができる仲間と共にねぇ
ＴＫと松下は
Where are T.K. and Matsushita?
保健室よ　二人の見張り
They're at the infirmary, standing guard.
Actually kinda surprising to know that T.K. totally sucks at English.
ＴＫはあれで全然英語だめだからなぁ
データをすべて消して　ログインパスワードを変え
So, what you're trying to accomplish here is to wipe the data,
change the username and password, and seal away all the abilities?
すべての能力を封じる　ということか
だがそれも一時凌ぎでしかない
That will only be a temporary measure.
You understand that, don't you?
分かってんのか
Yeah, I do.
分かってる　いつか突破されて　またデータが打ち込まれる
She'll crack through all of that and eventually rewrite the program.
ならばマシンごと破壊してしまえばいい
Then we should break the machine itself.
マシンはコンピュータ室の備品として
There are plenty of replacements in the computer room that are school property.
いくらでも代わりはあるわの
Same goes with the software.
ソフトも同様
Just great.
くそ
Hey, you all sound smart today.
ありゃ　今日の皆さんは頭よさそうですよ
Did you eat something rotten?
悪いものでも食べましたか
All we can do now is wait.
後は　天命を待つだけねぇ
Whose side will God take?
果たして　神は誰に味方するのか
Crap. I'm late for the exam.
やべッ　過ぎてんじゃ　センター試験
Hang on.
しっかり
Hey!
おいッ！  大丈夫か
Are you all right?
I feel a little dizzy.
少しふらふらする
Your head is bleeding.
額から　血が出ってる
意識は
Feeling faint?
大丈夫
I'm fine.
Anything feel strange? Nauseous at all?
気分は　吐き気とかあるか
大丈夫
No.
Are you a doctor or something?
なんだ　あんた医者か
まさか　ただの学生だよ
No way. I'm just a student.
Can you get up?
立てるか
Yeah...
うん
Let's get out.
出よう
Still all right?
大丈夫か
Yeah. Thanks.
うん　すまない
Horrible...
ひでー
ああ  とにかく助けを
Yeah.
Anyway, I'll call for help.
Damn it...
くそ
駄目か
No luck?
中に残ってる人たちを助けよう
Let's save those who are still left inside.
I'll help you.
手伝おう
大丈夫か
Can you?
I feel a little wobbly, but I should be fine.
まだ少しいふらつくが
I'm Igarashi.
五十嵐だ
I'm Otonashi.
音無
Let's hurry.
急ごう
Will we be okay?
助かるのかなぁ
大丈夫
I'll go look for an exit.
出口を見てくる
出られたら助けを呼んでくる
If I make it out, I'll get some help.
I'll be sure to come back. I'll borrow this light.
そうしたら必ず戻ってくるから
ライトを少し借りる
Yeah! Thanks!
ああ　頼む
Otonashi!
音無　絶対助かろう
Let's make sure to get out of this!
ああ
Yeah!
くそ
Damn it!
What the hell is this...?
なんだよ　これ
音無　どうだった
Otonashi!
How was it?
It looks a little difficult.
ちょっと難しい
I see.
そっか
Listen to me, everyone!
皆　聞いてくれ
The tunnel is closed off with rubble here and at the back, too.
トンネルは前も後ろも土砂で塞がってる
Our cell phones won't connect, either.
携帯も繋がらない
外との連絡は取れない
We can't get in touch with the outside.
From here on, we work together.
ここからは一心同体
一人だけ助かろうなんてことは考えないでほしい
I don't want anyone trying to survive alone.
食料と水を集めて　平等に分け合おう
We'll gather all the food and water we have, and we'll share it equally.
ちょっと待て
Wait a moment!
いつからお前が仕切ることになったんだ
Since when did you become the leader?!
Then who will?!
じゃ誰が仕切る
怪我人の看病の指揮を誰が取る
Who will head up nursing the injured?
He's got medical knowledge.
こいつには医療の知識がある
まさか怪我人は放置なんてことはないよなぁ
You're not saying to leave the injured people behind, are you?
T-That's not what I meant, but...
そッ　それはないけどよ
Help will definitely come.
必ず助けがくる　それまでの辛抱だ
We need to hang tight until then.
一緒に頑張ろう
Let's all survive through this!
喉が乾いたら言ってくれ
Let me know when you get thirsty.
食事は定時になったら伝える
We'll hand out food when the time comes.
気分が悪いやつは　音無を呼んでくれ
Anyone who feels sick, let Otonashi know.
もう少しの辛抱ですよ
Please hang in there a little longer.
Let me know if there's anything you need.
何かあったら　呼んでください
Thanks.
音無
Otonashi.
うん
How is our food supply?
食糧は
手作り弁当とお菓子が少し
One packed lunch and some snacks.
飲み物はペットボトルのお茶と 水が五六本ってところかな
We've got one bottle of tea, and I'd guess about five or six bottles of water.
That could last us for three days.
以て三日か
それにしても　お前すげーなぁ
But man, you're amazing.
うん　何が
How so?
You're so dedicated.
なんて献身的なんだよ
ＮＰＯで海外でも行く気か
You plan on going abroad with some NPO?
I hadn't really considered anything like that...
いや　そんなつもりはねぇけど
冗談だよ　真に受けんなって
I'm just joking with you. Don't take it so seriously.
But you should save your energy, too. You'll be the first on your knees.
でも自分の体力も温存しとけよ
真っ先に倒れるぞ
Yeah.
ああ
Hey!
おい　てっめー
You!
He took the water!
あいつ水を
Wait!
まてまて
Bastard!
くそが
The water!
水が
よせ
Stop it!
W-What's wrong, Leader-sama?
なんっ　なんだよ　リーダー様
You going to restrain me or something?
俺を拘束でもしようってんのかよ
Sure! Go ahead!
好きにしろよ
No one's going to live through this!
どうせも誰も助からねぇんだからなぁ
なぁ　皆も分かってんだろう
I mean, you all know that, don't you?!
That's not true. We'll be rescued.
そんなことはない　助かる
Quit being such a nice guy!
綺麗事だ
That guy just wasted our water!
今　その子が大切な水を
大丈夫だ
It's fine.
今のは俺の分だ
That was just my share.
I won't drink anything from here out.
もう俺は今後一切飲まないから　だから安心してくれ
So you all can relax.
Someone punch him! I can't calm down otherwise!
誰かそいつを殴ってよ  こっちの気が済まない
Yeah, I'll give him a good one.
ああ　十分懲らしめておく
Don't worry. We'll share mine.
大丈夫だ　俺の分を二人わけるていこう
Sorry about that.
すまない
Not a problem.
ふん　気にすんな
Okay, let's take him somewhere.
よーし　じゃこいつどっかに移動させるぞ
You guys, give me a hand.
おい　てめえらも手伝え
Fine.
だよ
音無
Otonashi! Otonashi!
音無！
何かやばいんだ　来てくれ
Something looks wrong! Come see him!
くそ
Crap.
Come back to us.
戻れよ
Come back!
戻れ
くそ
Damn it.
What have I been working toward since that day?
あの日から　俺は何を頑張ってきたんだ
あいつに
She... Hatsune taught me the meaning of life.
初音に生きる意味を教えられて
それで　また人の命を目の前で失って
And then... more life was lost right before my eyes...
Nothing has changed.
何も変わっちゃいない
I'm still powerless.
俺は無力なままじゃないか
Nothing has changed since that day.
あの時から　何も変わっちゃいないじゃないか
Damn.
くそ
くそッ！
Damn it!
Shouldn't you rest some already?
もう休んだほうがいいんじゃねぇか
I want to read a little more.
もうちょっと読みたい
Oh, fine.
仕方ねぇな
There.
ほら　風邪でも引いたらことだからな
We don't want you catching a cold.
でも　どうしてよくならねぇのかな
But, why won't you get any better?
If only we could find a donor.
ドナーがいればいいんだけどね
ドナー
A donor?
Igarashi.
五十嵐
Do you have a pen on you?
サインペンあるか
Yeah.
Circle the organs to donate at the time of your death.
Circle the organs to donate
nashi   Yuzuru
ふん　まったくよ
Unbelievable.
What the heck are you doing?
んだよそれ
If I do this, even if my life ends, it will be used for someone else's life.
こうしておけば
自分の命がもし尽きても
それでも　その命が人のために使われる
We can leave behind a little meaning in our lives.
生きてきた意味が作れるんだ
You know... you really are amazing, Otonashi.
なあ
やっぱお前はすげぇーよ
音無　見ろよ
Look. They were all in the depths of despair, and now they're leaving hope for others.
あれだけ絶望してた連中がみんな
誰かに希望を託そうとしてる
お前がみんなの人生を作ったんだぜ
You saved everyone's life.
音無
Otonashi...
Hey, Otonashi...
なあ　音無
Are you listening?
聞いてんのかよ
Otonashi...
音無
Kanade!
奏
お前なぁ　心配したんだぞ
I was so worried about you!
Are you okay! Is there anything wrong with you?!
大丈夫か　体は平気か
壮絶な戦いだった
The battle was fierce.
"Battle"?
戦い
It's a miracle that the me who made that promise to you is the one who woke up.
あなたと約束したアタシが目覚めたのは奇跡ってこと
Hey, I remember everything now.
なあ　俺 全部思い出したよ
死んだときのこと
How I died.
On the way to my exam, I got caught in a train accident.
センター試験の会場に向かう途中
列車の事故に巻き込まれてさ
I wanted to become a doctor.
俺　医者になりたかったんだ
誰かのためになりたい
I wanted to be of help to others. I wanted to live hearing "thank you".
ありがとうって言ってもらえるように生きたいって
そう思って　結構必死に勉強したんだけどな
That's how I began.
I studied a lot, too.
でもさ
But, in the end, I left my body behind in that world with my organs up for donation.
俺は最後にこの体をドナー登録で残せたんだ
俺の体は誰かを助けてあげられたはずだ
My body should have saved someone.
そう信じる
I'll believe that it did.
I'm sure that certain someone will forever say "thank you" to you.
きっとその誰かは見知らないあなたに
ありがとうって一生思い続けるわね
結弦
Yuzuru.
なんだ
What is it?
ならもう　思い残すことはない？
You don't have any more regrets?
That's true. If I was able to save someone, then my life wasn't so bad.
そうだな
誰かを助けられたなら
俺の人生はそう悪いものじゃなかった
I can think that way now.
そう思えるよ
Does this mean... Am I going to disappear?
もしかして　俺は消えるのか
If you have nothing more to regret.
思い残すことがなければ
But they're here.
あいつらがいる
I see. You want to continue to be with them?
そう　あの人たちとずっと一緒にいたい
Well, they're my friends. So of course I do.
それは　仲間だからな　いたいさ
でも　今は違う気持ちもある
But I've got something else on my mind, too.
I wish that everyone could overcome their lives like I did, and exit this world together.
あいつらも俺みたいな報われた気持ちになってさ
みんなで　この世界から去れればいいなって
I don't think a new life would be all that bad.
また新しい人生も悪くないってさ
Right?
でしょ
Yeah.
あっ
ちょっと待って
Wait a minute! Is this the feeling you wanted everyone to understand?
お前はもしかして
この気持ちをみんなに知ってほしかったのか
知らなかった
You didn't know?
Of course I didn't!
知らねえよ
つーか　俺
Think! I was stabbed by you the first time we met!
あった途端いきなりぶっ刺されたんだぞ
Well, you asked me to prove to you that no one could die.
だって　あなたが死なないことを証明しろって言うから
なんて空回りをしてきたんだ
What a long road she and the rest of them have been taking.
こいつとあいつらは
And just how bad can she be with communication?
そしてこいつの不器用さといったら
You're saying we'll become happy if we take classes?!
真面目に授業を受けたら幸せなのか
部活動をしたら　満たされるのか
That we'll feel content if we participate in club activities?!
Yes, since all those that come here are ones who couldn't live out their youthful days.
だって　ここに来るのはみんな
青春時代をまともに過ごせなかった人たちだもの
Really?
そうなのか
知らなかった
You didn't know?
I didn't!
知らねえよ
How was I even supposed to figure that out?!
つか　そんなこと　どうやったらわかるんだよ
You didn't notice that from the way things were designed?
見てて気付かなかった
Now I get it.
そうか
This was a place to save young souls.
ここは若者たちの魂の救済場所だったんだ
If Hinata had caught that fly ball, he would have been fulfilled and disappeared.
日向も　あのセカンドフライを取っていれば
報われて消えていたんだ
What a bother Yui and I were.
なんてお節介をしちまったんだ　俺と唯は
岩沢はそれを自分の力で達成して報われて消えていた
Iwasawa accomplished the task herself. She achieved satisfaction and disappeared.
誰もここに居たくているんじゃない
Nobody's here because they want to be.
We're all fighting against how unfair life is.
人生の理不尽に抗っているだけなんだ
それを奏はそうじゃないと
But Kanade says that's not true.
理不尽じゃない人生を教えてあげたくて
She wanted to show us a fair life.
人並みの青春を送らせてあげたくて
She wanted us to have a normal student life.
That's why she kept trying to persuade those who tried to remain here.
ここにとどまろうとする彼らを説得してきた
それが
It was all for...
なんて皮肉な話だ
How ironic.
That was all to get us to realise her point, but instead we fought against each other to cling to our individual beliefs,
それだけの話だったのに
お互いの信念を貫くため対立し
やがて武器まで作り出して
and eventually it escalated to the point of making weapons.
今じゃ抗争の毎日だ
Now, we're basically fighting every day.
Just how bad at communicating are you?
どんだけ不器用なんだよ　おまえ
I know I'm bad.
知ってる
So you're at least aware of it.
自覚あんだな
Yeah.
うん
でももし
But I think if you're here with me... I might be able to accomplish it.
あなたがいてくれたら　できるかもしれない
So you're asking me to help?
それは　手伝えってことか
本当ならあなたは消えてるはず
You honestly should already have disappeared. However, you're still here.
でも　あなたは残っている
Does that mean I'll be the first person who's able to stay with you?
お前の初めての味方になれるのか　俺は
あなたが思い残してることはそのことじゃないの
Isn't that what's actually bothering you the most?
Yeah...
そうかもしれない
Maybe...
But...
でも
Until that day, I was confident that I was being a good sister, too.
あの日までは立派なお姉ちゃんでいられた自信もあったのに
守りたい全てを３０分で奪われた
I had everything I wanted to protect taken from me in a matter of 30 minutes.
I just can't accept something so unreasonable.
そんな理不尽ってないじゃない
I can't forgive being given such a life.
そんな人生なんて許せないじゃない
無理だ
It's impossible.
I mean, even more so!
いや　だからこそ
そんな記憶を永遠に背負い続けていこうとしてる
Because she's fighting to carry on that memory forever, I want to help her.
あいつだからこそ
救ってやりたい
できるんだろか　この不器用な天使と
Can Tenshi and I really manage to do that?
It's not promising at all. It really may be impossible.
頼りねえ
やっぱ　無理か
But if we don't do it, the fight will continue.
いや　だったら抗争は続くぞ
What should I do?
どうすればいい
あいつらの仲間であり　奏の味方でもいられる俺が
I'm a part of them, but I'm also Kanade's friend, so isn't this something meant for me to do?
何とかしなきゃいけないんじゃないのか
なあ　協力してくれるか
Hey, could you help me out?
それは　こっちのセリフじゃない
Shouldn't I be the one saying that?
Oh. Yeah, right.
そっか　そうだよな
What am I saying?
天使に何言ってんだ　俺
わかったよ　奏
Okay, Kanade.
卒業させよう　ここから皆を
We'll get the others to graduate.
We'll make sure everyone graduates from this world.
そういうわけで
So, we discovered that there were people who swapped every one of Tachibana's tests in an attempt to soil her.
全科目のテストの答案用紙をすり替え
立花を貶めようとした連中がいたことが　わかった
Tachibana has illuminated the discrepancy in the handwriting, proven her point,
立花自ら筆跡の不一致を証明したことにより
立花の潔白を証明され
and as such will be working again as the student council president.
いつも一人で歩いてた
再びわが校の生徒会長として復帰することになった
ついては生徒会長代理として
As a result, Naoi, who has been working as the deputy president, will be returning to the seat of vice president.
振り返るとみんなは遠く
●
尽力してくれた直井は副会長として
ああ　もう
●
Why do I have to do this?
なんでぼくがこんな目に
それでも私は歩いたそれが強さだった
She managed to get all of us in trouble.
一人残さず暴きだしやがった
．
●
What good was all that flying?
あの錐もみ飛行はなんだったんですか
．
Yeah! Seriously!
だよな
●
おや　珍しく意見が合いましたね
Oh. How rare that our opinions coincide.
やらされたやつにしかわからねえよ　この気持ちは
Of course, since only those who took flight would understand.
●
We're flying buddies!
俺達は錐もみ飛行仲間さ
もう何も 怖くない
Whoa, there. Do you intend to undress me?
おっと　私を脱がす気ですか
Sure! Strip away!
おっほう　脱いでやれ　脱いでやれ
やめなさいよ　うるさい
Stop it. You're being loud.
そうつぶやいてみせる
そうだ　気持ち悪い　やめろ
Yeah! And it's gross, so quit it!
どっちですか
Which is it?
On another note, it looked like she forgot everything that happened these past few days.
にしても　あの子
もうここ数日のこと
全部忘れちゃったみたいだったね
It's only natural she does,
since the 100 won.
当然です　百のほうが勝ったんですから
いつか　人は一人になって
．
Those who attacked us won.
われわれを襲ったほうが
本当に一瞬仲間になれるかなって思っちまったぜ
I seriously thought that we might be able to get along.
ああ　くそ
Damn it!
思い出の中に生きてくだけ
．
I will have to hear what happened to them in the past, first.
まずはあいつらから過去の話を聞き出さなければならない
でも　敵を失った今のままじゃ
But now that we don't have an enemy to keep an eye on, I can't sneak around Yuri.
孤独さえ愛し笑ってられるように
．
百合の目を盗んで動くことは不可能だ
So Kanade, I need you to return to being the student council president.
だから　奏　お前は生徒会長に戻ってほしい
私は戦うんだ
また奴らと　戦ってほしい
I need you to fight against them again.
When you do, I need you to do as I tell you.
そして　俺の指示通り動いてほし
うん　私に向いてる作戦ね
This sounds like a fitting strategy for me.
涙なんて見せないんだ
また一人にしてしまうけど　ごめん
Sorry, I'll be leaving you alone again.
でも　すべてが終わったら
But when everything's over-
When it's over?
終わったら
When...
その時
When that happens, what will happen to us?
その時俺達はどうなるんだろ
I've always walked this path alone; when I look back, everyone is so far away.
itsumo hitori de aruiteta furikaeru to minna ha tooku
いつもひとりで歩いてた　振り返るとみんなは遠く
Even so, I kept on walking. That was my strength.
soredemo atashi ha aruita sore ga tsuyosa datta
それでもあたしは歩いた　それが強さだった
"Nothing frightens me any longer", I mumble softly.
mou nanimo kowakunai sou tsubuyaitemiseru
もう何も恐くない　そう呟いてみせる
Eventually, everyone ends up alone,
itsuka hito ha hitori ni natte
いつか人は一人になって
And is left with only their memories.
omoide no naka ni ikiteku dake
思い出の中に生きてくだけ
In order to appreciate even sorrow and continue smiling,
kodoku sae aishi waratterareru you ni
孤独さえ愛し笑ってられるように
I'll keep on fighting,
atashi ha tatakaunda
あたしは戦うんだ
I won't show you my tears.
namida nante misenainda
涙なんて見せないんだ
Next Episode Preview
Your guitar performance is killing the band.
"Tenshi." How dare she?!
She can tell the notes.
I knew she was special!
It's only one of the many things that I've wanted to do.
German Suplex!!
Prepare yourself!
Was the dumbass cured?
We men will win!
Just whose side are you on?!
Kiss you!
It's a miracle!!
Okay! I'll grant those wishes!
He took... all my happiness away...